Guide to the Master of Fine Arts in Experimental and Documentary Arts collection, 2012-2020 RL.11067
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- MFA/EDA Theses, 2017
  - Written Theses, 2017
    - Xin, Ran, 2017 (Box 15)
      Companion piece to an art and video installation exploring the landscapes and lives of people living in a small town near Beijing, China, the effects of modernization, and the expose` of a pyramid scheme. The written thesis includes images from the installation, as well as stills from the film.
    - Zhu, Yijie, 2017 (Box 15)
      Best Time: An Autobiographical Insight and Other Stories
      From the artist's statement: "My thesis project, 'The One,' examines the turning point of China's grand government family planning at the end of 2015, and discusses the influence of the former One Child Policy on the younger generation born in the 80s and 90s. It is an integrated project that employs digital film, photography, archives, print, and writing."
      The written thesis includes color images of the installation and photographic content.
    - Zhao, Haoyang, 2017 (Box 24)
      Tomato Republic
      This uniquely constructed photobook explores expressions and interpretations of art in conjunction with modern life in China, Singapore, the U.K., and the United States. Measuring approximately 11x17.5 inches, it contains reproductions of photographs as well as still images from events and a short videofilm. From the artist's statement: "I am concerned with technologies of display and presentation. My attempt to bridge dream and reality lie in the combination of the physical exhibit of the book object, my bodily interaction with the book that creates a temporal flow of still images, as well as the virtual images that constitute a participatory and observatory experience."
  - Creative Theses, 2017
    - Al-Ismaili, Salima, 2016-2017, Taken in part from artist's statement: Shadows of Devotion is an exploration into women's leadership and feminine spirituality in Islam. This exhibit brings together three bodies of work in conversation with one another: "Nests of the Nu Ahong," 11 color digital photographic prints of women; "prayers," a performance piece on video; and "من وراء حجاب" (from behind a veil), embroidered panels documented in the collection with seven digital photographs. The body of work was created in 2016-2017 as an exploration into women's leadership in Islam, which prompted visiting and documenting the women's mosques in China and resulted in creating the installations as a response to the experience. "Shadows of Devotion" brings together documentary photography, textile art, and performances to share a glimpse into the anatomy of Muslim women transcending into spiritual autonomy.; 11 color inkjet prints; 7 digital photograph files; 1 digital video file (4:51 MP4); approximately 3 gigabytes.
      - Nests of the Nu Ahong, 2016 (Box 15)
        From the artist's statement: "The 11 photographs in "Nests of the Nu Ahong" were taken in women's mosques (nusi) in China's Henan province (Zhenghzhou & Kaifeng) and the community of Hui Muslim minorities they serve. Under the echoes of the call to prayer, whispering women gather under the leadership of the nu ahong. The nu ahong carry on the 300-year-old tradition of educating Muslim women in their communities through teaching Islamic jurisprudence, reading and interpreting the Quran, performing the Friday sermons and initiating the five daily prayers. This series explores the predominantly aging community of women that congregate, and the future of the nu ahong as they struggle to attract a younger generation."
      - من وراء حجاب (from behind a veil), 2016-2017; 18 digital images (TIFF and JPEG formats); approximately 1.2 gigabytes. (Digital-materials RL11067-SET-0012)
        These digital photoraphs (available in file format only) document embroidered panels created by the artists.
      - prayers, 2017, Video file (MP4 format); approximately 1.1 gigabytes. (Digital-materials RL11067-SET-0012)
        One digital video file. From the artist's description: "prayers is a performance piece that explores converging existing and non-existing prayer poses that mold over time...Inspired by the women's mosques in China and their women-led leadership, Al-Ismaili employs religious gestural performance as a means of accessing internalized spiritual memory as traveled through generations of women before her."
    - Borst, Sarah Elizabeth, 2017, (Taken from the artist's description) This is Mine comes in four parts: one book, "Part I: The Diaries," curated from Borst's personal archive of family photographs, love letters from boys, journal entries since middle school and interactions with social media. "Part II: Adult in Training," is a feature length film where Borst documented herself on camera since September of 2015 in moments of transition into the construct of adulthood. In "Part III: The Monologue," a short film, Borst comes to terms with her personal history of rape and sexual harassment through intimately sharing stories from her past. "Part IV: Milk," is a series of color 13x19 inch photographs of mothers breastfeeding in their homes.; 25 items: 1 book, 2 digital .mov files (42 and 5 minutes), 22 color inkjet prints
      Biographical / Historical
      Sarah Elizabeth Borst (born 1993, Long Island, New York) is an internationally exhibited feminist artist working in the mediums of photography, film, installation and performance art. She received her Bachelor of Fine Arts Degree in Photography from Savannah College of Art and Design, and is a 2017 graduate of the Master of Fine Arts in Experimental and Documentary Arts program at Duke University. In addition to her credits as an artist, she is the curator for the Provost's Hall Gallery at Duke University working under the Provost, Sally Kornbluth, as well as the Director of the Center for Documentary Studies, Wesley Hogan. She is also an Editorial Assistant for Aint-Bad Magazine, an independent publisher of new photographic art. In 2017 Borst taught the Black and White Photography summer course at the Center for Documentary Studies at Duke.
      Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
      Inkjet prints were produced using an Epson 9900 printer and Epson Ultrachrome HDR ink on Museo Silver Rag paper.
      - This is Mine, 2017, 22 color prints; Document files (PDF format), Moving image files (MOV format), and still images (TIFF and JPEG format); approximately 86 gigabytes. (Box 23, Digital-materials RL11067-SET-0014)
        These 13x19 inch color inkjet photographs belong to Part IV, "Milk," and portray women breastfeeding in their homes.
    - Zhao, Haoyang, 2016-2017, Comprises 20 13x19 inch untitled color giclee photographic prints from the series Tomato Republic; a small handmade accordion photobook with red-tone transparency reproductions on handmade paper, on display in the Tomato Republic exhibition at SPECTRE Art; and a digital film (total running time 6:47 minutes) entitled Chinatown Development. From the artist's description: "Tomato Republic has its origination in advertising aesthetics, taking found images and re-appropriating as new photographic creations. It is an order I found while I was wandering the streets of Beijing in the summer of 2016. That summer, I was travelling across cities in China, Singapore, the United Kingdom and the United States. I told myself that I was visiting friends and recovering memories from places that I shared much of my adolescent and early adult years. It is a great excuse to be around places, ones that have occupied a permanent place in my mind, ones that constantly drifted from one transient stage to another pushed and pulled by economic development. It became another phase of creation of memories, manifested in the form of photographic images. The accordion photobook is made from educational slides for studies of Chinese religions from Yale Divinity School, acquired from online vendors. The transparency scans were made and printed on handmade washi paper. The film Chinatown Development served as the precursor to the larger project, where archival salvaging of Internet videos meets a personal exploration of an obsolete shopping mall that would have become a Chinatown."
      Haoyang Zhao was born and raised in Xi'an, China. After four years of high school in Singapore, he moved to London to study Economics, while also working as a freelance photographer and cinematographer for a student feature film ACT I. In 2013 Haoyang attended Georgetown University as an exchange student, studying photography and film studies alongside courses in economics and political science. He served as the Project Manager for Social Practice Lab at Franklin Humanities Institute. He holds a Bachelor of Science degree in Economics from University College London, and graduated from the Master of Fine Arts in Experimental and Documentary Arts program at Duke University in May, 2017.
      - Tomato Republic (Box 24)
        Project comprises photographic prints and an accordion photobook.
      - Chinatown Development, Video file (Pro Res format), approximately 5 gigabytes. (Digital-materials RL11067-SET-0012)
    - Pesci, Colleen F., 2017
      Comprises one digital film file, running time 23:08 minutes, titled Companion. The film was screened at Shadowbox Studio on March 26, 2017 as part of Pesci's MFA thesis exhibition.
      The artist writes: "Companion is a look into the complicated process of grief. The film features four individuals speaking about the death of their twins. These losses occurred at various ages and under diverse circumstances; in their retelling, the spectator is brought into moments or rawness lined with hope. Weaved in and out of the individuals' reflections is a personal letter to my own twin, touching on the fragility of life."
      - Companion, 2017; Video file (MOV format), approximately 13 gigabytes. (Digital-materials RL11067-SET-0015)
    - Mueller, Lauren, 2017
      Huro Huro, which means "gibbon" in Garo, the language of the indigenous people of Tura, presents three conservation centers in India, Thailand and the United States committed to preserving gibbons. The film (running time 60 minutes) explores their disparate perspectives on conservation and raises questions about the effectiveness of varied practices and philosophies.
      - Huro huro, Video file (MOV format), approximately 37 gigabytes. (Digital-materials RL11067-SET-0016)
    - Herbold, Sylvia, 2017
      Thesis consists of an experimental documentary film (running time 20 minutes) exploring through improvised movements and physical gestures the perceptions of women and animals in landscapes.
      - A Path Seems Like A Place, 2017; Video file (MOV format), approximately 23 gigabytes. (Digital-materials RL11067-SET-0015)
- MFA/EDA Theses, 2018
  Series contains Duke University Master of Fine Arts in Experimental Documentary Arts theses from the class of 2018. The projects are listed in two groups, Written Theses and Creative Theses, and within are listed in alphabetical order by the students' last names.
  Electronic materials in this series have been migrated from original media to a library server and digital use copies can only be accessed onsite in the Rubenstein Library Reading Room. Please contact the library before coming to use this collection.
  - Written Theses, 2018
    This subseries contains the written theses submitted by the MFA EDA Class of 2018 whose work is part of this archive. Submission of projects to the archive is voluntary. Theses are typescripts unless otherwise noted; titles are included when known.
    - Bass, Lexi (Box 26)
    - Clements, Kaley (Box 26)
      Includes a paper copy of the inventory for his digital media work described in the Creative Theses subseries.
    - Dooney, Phyllis (Box 26)
    - Dunsmore, Summer (Box 26)
    - Jessen, Rachel (Box 26)
    - Kim, Danny (Box 26)
    - King, Katie (Box 26)
    - Lange, Jeremy (Box 26)
    - Scott, Theresa (Box 26)
    - Sonne, Laurids Andersen (Box 26)
    - Stevens, Nadia (Box 26)
    - Zheng, Xingyao (Box 26)
  - Creative Theses, 2018
    Subseries contains the creative theses submitted by the MFA EDA Class of 2018. Artists' statements and abstracts are included when provided; if there are only digital files and no physical location in the Creative Theses box, the artists' statement can be found in the Written Theses folder for that student.
    Electronic records in this sub-series have been migrated to a library server and digital use copies can only be accessed onsite in the Rubenstein Library Reading Room. To request access, please contact the Rubenstein Library before coming to use these records.
    There are also some individual restrictions on access; please consult the entries for each project.
    - Bass, Lexi, 2018
      Collection includes one 65-minute digital video, titled How Bluebirds Are Born. The film was screened at Full Frame Theater in Durham, North Carolina on March 30, 2018. One still image from the film, in jpeg format, is also included.
      The artist writes: "...overall, whether I am creating imagery with Mordançage-processed silver prints, foam board masks, fallen tree branches, or light, my work is always a deep analysis of the damaged psyche and the transformation of a suffering identity to one that transcends its suffering by naming its own changing shape."
      - How bluebirds are born, Video file (MP4 format) and still image (JPEG format), approximate runtime 65 minutes; approximately 4.3 gigabytes. (Digital-materials RL11067-SET-0001)
    - Clements, Kaley, 2017-2018
      This collection includes the March 31, 2018 screening cut of Low Hanging Fruit, and the original audiovisual and audio files used to edit the piece for the thesis screening edition. It also contains additional footage that was shot for this ongoing project, but not used in the thesis screening version.
      The film follows avocados as a commodity in Michoacán, the only state in Mexico allowed to export the product into the USA. It uncovers the influence of cartels and related violence; social conflicts; and environmental problems spurring migration into the United States.
      Restricted access until 2048.
      - Low hanging fruit, Video file (MP4 format), approximate runtime 32 minutes; approximately 6.8 gigabytes. (Digital-materials RL11067-SET-0002)
    - Dooney, Phyllis B., 2017-2018
      This collection explores black families and individuals descended from enslaved people on Stagville plantation in northern Durham County, North Carolina. It comprises 38 black-and-white archival pigment prints measuring 16x16 inches, from Dooney's thesis exhibition at the Carrack in Durham, N.C., Spring 2018, chiefly portraits but also street scenes in Durham. These are accompanied by 54 audio files with oral history interviews of Stagville plantation descendants. Finally, there is also one moving image piece (running time 15:49 minutes), digitized from 16mm film that is designed to run on a projector in a loop.
      - Photographs, 2017-2018 (Box 27)
      - Digital video and audio files, 2018; Video file (Apple ProRes format), approximate runtime 16 minutes, and 54 audio files (WAV format); approximately 38.4 gigabytes. (Digital-materials RL11067-SET-0003)
    - Jessen, Rachel, 2017-2018
      GIRL WRESTLE is a visual exploration of girls' youth wrestling in North Carolina. The project series consists of a six-image portrait series showcasing individual wrestlers shot on a 4x5 field camera; a working edit of 40 to 50 smaller photographic prints from club practices and team tournaments, captured with digital and analog mediums; and an abstracted moving image piece which explores the intimacy and sensuality inherent to the sport, shot on 16mm film. Scenes captured from practice and meets combine with portraits of wrestlers to create a holistic view of the distinct individuals that have been brought together by love of the sport.
      - GIRL WRESTLE 15x19 inch portraits, 6 photographs (Box 27)
      - GIRL WRESTLE smaller size prints, 36 photographs Dimensions vary, ranging from approximately 8 3/4 x 11 3/4 inches to 9x13 inches. (Box 28)
      - GIRL WRESTLE digital video, Video file (MOV container format), approximate runtime 9 minutes; approximately 0.5 gigabytes. (Digital-materials RL11067-SET-0003)
    - King, Katie, 2017-2018
      Collection includes one 116-page photobook and four digital moving image files from the exhibition A tangle of branches. A tangle of branches was exhibited at SPECTRE Arts in downtown Durham, NC from March 16-25th 2018.
      The artist writes: A tangle of branches explores interiority and communication using mental health as lens and landscape. In this multimedia installation, text, film, photographs, and audio combine to collapse boundaries between interior selves and exterior lives.
      - I must have decided wrongly [photobook], 2018 (Box 30)
      - A tangle of branches films, Four video files (MP4 format); approximately 3.0 gigabytes. (Digital-materials RL11067-SET-0001)
    - Lange, Jeremy, 2017-2018
      Collection contains 52 color digital inkjet prints from the thesis exhibition After Golden Leaf, as well as a trade version of a book produced from the same work. Lange's project, in his own words, "...explores the changing physical and cultural landscape of North Carolina as it attempts to accommodate the realities of the post-tobacco economy. The photographs investigate the history of tobacco farming as well as the future of the communities it has built."
      - After Golden Leaf [photographs], 52 photographs (Box 29)
      - After Golden Leaf [photobook] (Box 29)
    - Sonne, Laurids, 2018
      Sonne's creative thesis, entitled Man from Iota, comprises a digital film (running time 50 minutes), original drawings on paper and copies of drawings, and small sculptures of bones.
      In the artist's words, her project investigates the correspondence of time and the instance of man's existence in it, the desire for the unattainable freedom of flight within this instance, while being tethered to the rock of time and history, his own doing within it and his desire for quantifiable knowledge.
      - Drawings and sculptures of bones (Box 30)
      - Man from Iota, Video file (MOV container format), approximate runtime 50 minutes; approximately 30.2 gigabytes. (Digital-materials RL11067-SET-0001)
    - Stevens, Nadia, 2018
      Stevens' thesis, Dream of Angels is a body of work which consists of two short films, one video installation, a collection of 21 diptychs, and a photobook. The films, Historic Moments (12 min) and Kilonova (17 min), premiered as one program in that order. The diptychs, titled Familiar Aches, are a retroactive collaboration with Stevens' mother; half of the 35mm black and white photographs were made by her mother in 1985, the other half were made by the artist in 2015. Twenty-one diptychs are composed of 42 individual photographs, paired and presented as single images. They were installed in the Duke University's Rubenstein Arts Center's main gallery, along with a site-specific installation utilizing a symbolic funeral shroud, piled-up earth, and projected images of gravestone rubbings. Also included is a photobook documenting the paper trail of Stevens' family's tax-exempt Social Club (1975-1987), aptly named Family United, as well as a postcard used to publicize the screening and gallery reception.
      - Dream of Angels booklet and postcard (Box 30)
      - Familiar aches, 21 Files; 21 image files (TIFF format); approximately 1.4 gigabytes. (Digital-materials RL11067-SET-0001)
      - Historic moments, Video file (MP4 format), approximate runtime 12 minutes; approximately 1.6 gigabytes. (Digital-materials RL11067-SET-0001)
      - Kilonova, Video file (MP4 format), approximate runtime 17 minutes; approximately 1.7 gigabytes. (Digital-materials RL11067-SET-0001)
      - Dream of Angels, Video file (MP4 format), approximate runtime 11 minutes; approximately 0.5 gigabytes. (Digital-materials RL11067-SET-0001)
- MFA/EDA Theses, 2019; 2.5 Linear Feet 3 boxes; 102.5 Gigabytes 90 files
  Electronic records in this sub-series have been migrated to a library server and digital use copies can only be accessed onsite in the Rubenstein Library Reading Room. To request access, please contact the library before coming to use these records.
  - Written Theses, 2019
    This subseries contains the written theses submitted by the MFA EDA Class of 2019 whose work is part of this archive. Submission of projects to the archive is voluntary. Theses are typescripts unless otherwise noted; titles are included when known.
    - D'Agostino, David, 2019 (Box 31)
      Typescript thesis accompanying the film "Dixie Garden Drive."
    - Guo, Lishan, 2019 (Box 31)
      Typescript thesis accompanying the creative project "Space Tells."
    - Liu, Jinyu, 2019 (Box 31)
      Typescript thesis accompanying the creative project "The Factory."
    - Moss, Jacob, 2019 (Box 31)
      Typescript thesis accompanying the photographic documentary project "One Arm Dove Hunt."
    - Palma, Felicity, 2019 (Box 31)
      Typescript thesis accompanying the creative project "Fra la Medusa e l'abisso" ("Between Medusa and the Abyss").
    - Rachkovsky, Tamar, 2019 (Box 31)
      Typescript thesis accompanying the film "Home in E Major."
    - Riazati, Sarah, 2019 (Box 31)
      Typescript thesis accompanying the creative project "monumental."
    - Smith, Dani, 2019 (Box 32)
      Typescript thesis accompanying the creative project "West from Ruby to Rose," contained within a handmade wooden box created by the artist.
  - Creative Theses, 2019; 25 photographs; 102.5 Gigabytes 90 files 3 mov, 2 mp4, 6 mp3, 74 jpeg, 4 pdf, 1 docx files
    Subseries contains the creative theses submitted by the MFA EDA Class of 2019. Artists' statements and abstracts are included when provided; if there are only digital files and no physical location in the Creative Theses box, the artists' statement can be found in a Creative Theses folder for that student housed with the Written Theses.
    - Moss, Jacob, 2019; The color inkjet prints were created with an Epson 9900, using Epson Ultrachrome HDR ink on Museo Silver Rag paper.
      This MFA thesis consists of 25 inkjet color photographs from the project "One Arm Dove Hunt," which takes its name from a Texas mural photographed by the artist. Chiefly portraits of individuals with a rare genetic disease, the series also includes some landscapes and interior scenes. The images were taken in various U.S. locations, with a focus on California and other Western states. Eastern locations include New York and Ohio.
      Seven prints are sized 12 x 12 inches and 18 are 12 x 9.6 inches. They are smaller versions of prints exhibited in 2019 in Durham, NC.
      From the artist's statement: "Over the past year I have travelled through more than 25 states, connected with and photographed individuals with various forms of Ectodermal Dysplasia, a rare genetic condition that I myself have. The goal of One Arm Dove Hunt is to explore my relationship with Ectodermal Dysplasia (ED) and others affected by it. What does it means to be part of a community dictated by a medical condition? How does that impact an individual's sense of self? My photographs depict a group of very different people from across the United States who happen to have one big thing in common, and the journey that brought me to them..."
      - Photographs (Box 33)
    - Palma, Felicity, 2019
      Digital documentary film shot in Palermo, Sicily and other locations, submitted as an MFA 2019 thesis project. Includes an artist's inventory and statement in .pdf format.